Welcome back to A Push in Under 3
Minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. Hey there, do you remember that
whole Cold War thing that has been going
on for a while now? Well, it actually is
going to end in this video with the
collapse of the Soviet Union. Now,
really quickly, I want to say that the
dissolution of the Soviet Union is a
very complex topic, and there is way too
many reasons for it. So, just understand
that this video might be an
oversimplification. But anyway,
historians often like to blame three
people for the Soviet Union's collapse.
Ronald Reagan, Pope John Paul the
Second, and Mikhail Gorbachev. For
Reagan's side, the US will build a
massive military with increased
spending, focusing on defending against
nuclear missiles, and the program here
was called SDI or the nickname Star
Wars. Reagan also pushed strong
anti-communist rhetoric, even going as
far to call the Soviet Union a quote
evil empire. In fact, let's roll that
clip. To ignore the facts of history and
the aggressive impulses of an evil
empire.
>> Oof. Apply ice to the burned area, my
goodness. And finally, the last thing
here is that Reagan eventually worked
with the Soviet Union in a series of
meetings to reduce tensions. But moving
on, for Pope John Paul the Second, he
helped push anti-communist beliefs in
Poland and ignited a massive solidarity
movement, which was a big blow to the
Soviet Union. But the final person here,
and probably the most important, is
Mikhail Gorbachev, who was the leader of
the Soviet Union starting in 1985.
Basically, Gorbachev is not like his
predecessors. He was instead a lot less
strict. And by this point, the USSR is
struggling to keep up financially with
the US. In response, Gorbachev releases
government reforms that attempt to fix
society, but instead totally weaken the
Soviet government. And finally,
countries controlled under the Soviet
Union begin to break away until 1989,
where the Berlin Wall officially falls,
and a few years later, the Soviet Union
collapses, ending the Cold War. So, now
I want you to think about something.
Since there is no more USSR rival, the
US is going to be the most powerful
nation in the world. And after this,
it's also important to note the US is
still going to intervene around the
world for various reasons like
peacekeeping in regional conflicts. And
now I am sure you can imagine lots of
different debates about the US's role in
the world will start up. That's all for
this one though. On the screen now are
AP style questions for this topic. Pause
now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
Now it is only three more topics to go.